<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Day of the Worms</title>
    <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://davidrutland.uk" />
    <updated>2025-06-20T10:35:35+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>David Rutland</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://davidrutland.uk</id>

    <entry>
        <title>It&#x27;s the journey... not the destination</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/its-the-journey-not-the-destination/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/its-the-journey-not-the-destination/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/15/earworm.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-06-20T10:32:10+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/15/earworm.png" alt="Drawing of a man&#x27;s bloodied face against a backdrop of leaves. There are large worms attacking him and one entering his ear." />
                    This is how you die. On your back, with a broken leg and worms crawling over and into your body. Well, it's one of many ways you can die. Most of them involve trauma and worms. One will involve something approaching natural causes. As with&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/15/earworm.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Drawing of a man&#x27;s bloodied face against a backdrop of leaves. There are large worms attacking him and one entering his ear." /></p>
                <p>This is how you die. On your back, with a broken leg and worms crawling over and into your body.</p>
<p>Well, it's one of many ways you can die. Most of them involve trauma and worms. One will involve something approaching natural causes.</p>
<p>As with life, so with games. You're going to have to do a lot of things right just to stay alive, and even then, a good outcome isn't certain.</p>
<p>The destination is certain, but it's how you get there that counts.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Caution! wet floor!</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/caution-wet-floor/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/caution-wet-floor/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/fall_panel.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-06-18T10:20:49+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/fall_panel.png" alt="Pen drawing of a man on an overgrown allotment site falling over while carrying a bucket. He looks distressed." />
                    Falls can be dangerous at any age, and especially so when you're an elderly allotment gardener, without a working mobile phone. Doubly so (or more), when there are parasitic worms in the area, and the only people who could possibly help are aging zombies controlled&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/fall_panel.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Pen drawing of a man on an overgrown allotment site falling over while carrying a bucket. He looks distressed." /></p>
                <p>Falls can be dangerous at any age, and especially so when you're an elderly allotment gardener, without a working mobile phone.</p>
<p>Doubly so (or more), when there are parasitic worms in the area, and the only people who could possibly help are aging zombies controlled by those same worms.</p>
<p>Our gardener isn't having a good day, and it's about to get worse.</p>
<p>Fortunately, he can always load a previous save and try again!</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--full"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/fall_panel2.png" alt="" width="1282" height="750" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/responsive/fall_panel2-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/responsive/fall_panel2-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/responsive/fall_panel2-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/responsive/fall_panel2-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/responsive/fall_panel2-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/14/responsive/fall_panel2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Dangerous animals...</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/dangerous-animals/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/dangerous-animals/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/13/howl_the_owl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-06-16T14:41:44+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/13/howl_the_owl.png" alt="Stylised black ink drawing of an owl" />
                    Allotment sites are full of wild creatures, whether foxes digging out a burrow, and dying under your shed, or dedicated and dangerous predators looking for a bite to eat. And owls can start behaving awfully strangely during the mating season.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/13/howl_the_owl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Stylised black ink drawing of an owl" /></p>
                <p>Allotment sites are full of wild creatures, whether foxes digging out a burrow, and dying under your shed, or dedicated and dangerous predators looking for a bite to eat.</p>
<p>And owls can start behaving awfully strangely during the mating season.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Meet Mike</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/meet-mike/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/meet-mike/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/12/scotch_mike_day_of_the_worms.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-05-14T16:23:31+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/12/scotch_mike_day_of_the_worms.png" alt="Pen drawing of an allotment plot with a man&#x27;s head in the foreground. He has blood coming from his eyes and nose and a worm coming from his nose." />
                    Scotch Mike is the first person you meet in Day of the Worms. He's your friendly neighbour, but right now, he isn't so friendly - and you may notice there seems to be something hanging from his nose. Oh dear! You'll need to negate the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/12/scotch_mike_day_of_the_worms.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Pen drawing of an allotment plot with a man&#x27;s head in the foreground. He has blood coming from his eyes and nose and a worm coming from his nose." /></p>
                <p>Scotch Mike is the first person you meet in Day of the Worms. He's your friendly neighbour, but right now, he isn't so friendly - and you may notice there seems to be something hanging from his nose.</p>
<p>Oh dear!</p>
<p>You'll need to negate the threat before you can move on.</p>
<p>You can burn Mike alive, scrape his flesh from his bones with a rake, or decapitate him with a spade. Do you kill Scotch Mike in cold blood or can you find another way to save civilisation along with your own life?</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Yes, I know it's been three months since the last paltry update. I've been busy doing cool stuff.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Distractions galore!</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/distractions-galore/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/distractions-galore/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/glass-3-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-02-16T16:10:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/glass-3-2xl.png" alt="AGS interface with DOTW running" />
                    Welp. It's been exactly two months since I added any update to the blog - or even touched the game. To be fair to myself - or to give myself an excuse - there have been distractions. Mid-December was the run-up to Christmas, we were&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/glass-3-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="AGS interface with DOTW running" /></p>
                <p>Welp. It's been exactly two months since I added any update to the blog - or even touched the game.</p>
<p>To be fair to myself - or to give myself an excuse - there have been distractions. Mid-December was the run-up to Christmas, we were having an en-suite bathroom done, and then, just after Christmas, I acquired a 3D printer.</p>
<p>Since then, most of my free time has gone into designing, printing and using new things. These include wine racks, lithophane lamps, various useful accesories, and of course, repeating crossbows - which are incredible fun, and if Day of the Worms happens in real life, could be a great advantage against the zombie hordes..</p>
<p>Two months is a long time though, and Day of the Worms has been nagging for my attention at the back of my subconscious.</p>
<p>I've definnitely missed the chance to get the game into February's Steam Next as I had planned.</p>
<p>This morning, I scanned some drawings I made in December, and am incorporating them into the game.</p>
<p>It's not that impressive, and amounted to a broken window and a shard of glass, which will be useful later on.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/glass-3-2.png" alt="DotW open with AGS editor in the background" width="1914" height="949" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/responsive/glass-3-2-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/responsive/glass-3-2-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/responsive/glass-3-2-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/responsive/glass-3-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/responsive/glass-3-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11/responsive/glass-3-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>But it is <em>something</em>, and I'm ready to start work on the next area!</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Some UI changes</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/some-ui-changes/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/some-ui-changes/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/dotw_mouseover_popup-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-12-16T16:07:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/dotw_mouseover_popup-2xl.png" alt="black and white game interface, showing an allotment backgound. The invetory is open with the curor over a spade. The text label at the bottom of the screen reads, &#x27;Also known as a shovel, but you call a spade a spade.&#x27; " />
                    It's difficult to strike the balance between showing enough information when the player needs it, and cluttering up the interface. When the player is wandering around the world, we want the screen to be as clear as possible, to allow the player to choose to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/dotw_mouseover_popup-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="black and white game interface, showing an allotment backgound. The invetory is open with the curor over a spade. The text label at the bottom of the screen reads, &#x27;Also known as a shovel, but you call a spade a spade.&#x27; " /></p>
                <p>It's difficult to strike the balance between showing enough information when the player needs it, and cluttering up the interface.</p>
<p>When the player is wandering around the world, we want the screen to be as clear as possible, to allow the player to choose to look at and interact with objects, scenery, and other characters.</p>
<p>To this end, the inventory is hidden when not in use, and only appears when the mouse is very near to the top of the screen. This allows the player to click on objects wherever they are on the y axis.</p>
<p>Likewise, I think having object and hotspot descriptions visible on a simple mouseover will be distracting, especially when the player has already read the description and knows what it is and does.</p>
<p>Everything in the world that has a description can be looked at with the right mouse button. There are no pop-ups, and triggering the description by looking at the object or hotspot has to be a conscious decision. That you can trigger another action is indicated by the cursor showing an eye, hand, or mouth.</p>
<p>Inventory objects are another matter. The player has their inventory open for a reason, and being able to scan quick desciptions is important, and can give clues to gameplay. For instance, is a bucket full of water or empty? Inventory mouseover pops the gActionBar at the bottom to give a quick description of what the object is. Using right-click (usually the Look action) to display text would block the action - requiring two clicks in total, so now, right click does nothing. I figure that up to 12 words is easily enough for the action bar GUI.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/dotw_mouseover_popup-2-2.png" alt="DotW screem showing tooltip at the bottom of the screen" width="1282" height="721" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/dotw_mouseover_popup-2-2-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/dotw_mouseover_popup-2-2-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/dotw_mouseover_popup-2-2-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/dotw_mouseover_popup-2-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/dotw_mouseover_popup-2-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/10/responsive/dotw_mouseover_popup-2-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>The other advantage of this is that I don't need to define functions for each type of click on an inventory item, as everying is dealt with automatically. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>DoTW Steam page is live!</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/dotw-steam-page-is-live/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/dotw-steam-page-is-live/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/steam_page-2-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-12-14T16:06:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/steam_page-2-2xl.png" alt="Screenshot of DoTW Steam page" />
                    Sadly, you can't buy the game yet - because I haven't finished it, but the Day of the Worms Steam page has been approved, and is now live - which is nice, and I'm chuffed to have made it to this stage. The actual process&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/steam_page-2-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Screenshot of DoTW Steam page" /></p>
                <p>Sadly, you can't buy the game yet - because I haven't finished it, but the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1392940/Day_of_the_Worms/">Day of the Worms Steam page</a> has been approved, and is now live - which is nice, and I'm chuffed to have made it to this stage.</p>
<p>The actual process was pretty easy. I paid the dev fee years ago - when I was planning Day of the Worms as a pure Twine text adventure - and the page creation process mainly involved creating screenshots and library images of different sizes.</p>
<p>I'm going to carry on actually making the game in my spare time with an eye to a possible release date in June 2025 (edit from May 2025: "LOL"), and updating the Steam page with screenshots, descriptions, and so on. Of course, this blog will be updated much more frequently and continue to be the home to thoughts, development, images, and frustrations.</p>
<figure class="post__image">
<figure ><figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/steam_page-3.png" alt="Steam page for Day of the Worms" width="1920" height="1038" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/steam_page-3-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/steam_page-3-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/steam_page-3-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/steam_page-3-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/steam_page-3-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/9/responsive/steam_page-3-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<figcaption >Caption</figcaption>
</figure>
</figure>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Second area background art</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/second-area-background-art/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/second-area-background-art/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/main_background_720-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-12-12T16:05:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/main_background_720-2xl.png" alt="Pen drawing of an allotment path complete with bathtub toilet, fence, weeds, and gate. On the plot itself are a water butt, plants, and a polytunnel. All against a blue sky with clouds." />
                    The second area is a path between the first and second allotment plots, and contains much of what you'd see on a normal allotment site. There's a toilet with flowers, a bathtub to collect rainwater, weeds, a rather rough-and-ready fence, and a sturdy gate. Further&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/main_background_720-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Pen drawing of an allotment path complete with bathtub toilet, fence, weeds, and gate. On the plot itself are a water butt, plants, and a polytunnel. All against a blue sky with clouds." /></p>
                <p>The second area is a path between the first and second allotment plots, and contains much of what you'd see on a normal allotment site.</p>
<p>There's a toilet with flowers, a bathtub to collect rainwater, weeds, a rather rough-and-ready fence, and a sturdy gate. Further objects will be added as... objects.</p>
<p>Beyond the fence, you can see the second plot - there's a polytunnel, various plants, and a water butt. The polytunnel will have its own interior (complete with tomato plants), and there will also be a bench.</p>
<p>The image is currently layers, and I'm not looking forward to separating everything out to create the walkbehind masks. </p>
<p> </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/main_background_720-2-2.png" alt="Pen drawing of an allowment path complete with bathtub tpolet, fence, weeds, and gate. On the plot itself are a water butt, plants, and a polytunnel. All against a blue sky with clouds." width="1920" height="720" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/responsive/main_background_720-2-2-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/responsive/main_background_720-2-2-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/responsive/main_background_720-2-2-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/responsive/main_background_720-2-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/responsive/main_background_720-2-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/8/responsive/main_background_720-2-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>First area ACTUALLY complete</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/first-area-actually-complete/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/first-area-actually-complete/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/wormfigh1_look_closer-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-12-11T16:03:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/wormfigh1_look_closer-2xl.png" alt="Cartoonlike black and white image on a large, toothed, eyeless worm looking at the viewer. There is red blood around its mouth, and leaf litter in the background" />
                    Almost two weeks after posting that the first area was almost complete, I have actually completed the first area. My big mistake was neglecting to consider the implications of DOTW being a point and click adventure with interactive fiction elements. In practice, this means that that&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/wormfigh1_look_closer-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Cartoonlike black and white image on a large, toothed, eyeless worm looking at the viewer. There is red blood around its mouth, and leaf litter in the background" /></p>
                <p>Almost two weeks after posting that the first area was almost complete, I have <em>actually</em> completed the first area.</p>
<p>My big mistake was neglecting to consider the implications of DOTW being a point and click adventure with interactive fiction elements.</p>
<p>In practice, this means that that there are multiple paths the character can take, and multiple ways to get there. Sure, most of them end in death, but they all need menus, they all need artwork, and they all need to make sense.</p>
<p>Many of these are just entertaining diversions en route to a predetermined outcome, but they take time to create.</p>
<p>Next step is the outside of the second allotment plot. In earlier iterations, this was a different choice, but I'd like to give the player a brief respite after (unless they were very lucky) figuring out how not to die while repeatedly dying.</p>
<p>I'm pretty pleased with artwork for a few of the area endings.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper-wrapper"><div class="gallery">
<div class="gallery" data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="2" data-pswp-uid="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/gallery/wormsquash.png" data-size="1280x748"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/gallery/wormsquash-thumbnail.png" alt="Black and white drawing of a shoe crushing a worm covered in blood" width="768" height="449"></a>
<figcaption>The shoe was moderately satisfying to draw</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/gallery/cannibalworms.png" data-size="1280x748"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/gallery/cannibalworms-thumbnail.png" alt="black and white cartoonish drawing of three worms with teeth surrounding a smaller worm. There is red blood on the worm and leaf litter in the background" width="768" height="449"></a>
<figcaption>Uh Oh!</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/gallery/wormfigh1_look_closer.png" data-size="1283x751"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/gallery/wormfigh1_look_closer-thumbnail.png" alt="Cartoonlike black and white image on a large, toothed, eyeless worm looking at the viewer. There is red blood around its mouth, and leaf litter in the background" width="768" height="450"></a>
<figcaption>You're gonna die</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/gallery/noseworm.png" data-size="1280x751"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/7/gallery/noseworm-thumbnail.png" alt="A drawing of a worm tail disappearing up a man's nose. Red blood drips down" width="768" height="451"></a>
<figcaption>You died.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
</div>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>First room almost completed - and more assets</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/first-room-almost-completed-and-more-assets/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/first-room-almost-completed-and-more-assets/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/6/foot_main-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-11-30T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/6/foot_main-2xl.png" alt="Black and white pen and ink drawing of an enormous shoe" />
                    Technically, it's the first and the second room - but the second room is the interior of a shed within the first room, so I don't think I can count that. There are still some very minor bugs to be worked out, and I need&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/6/foot_main-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Black and white pen and ink drawing of an enormous shoe" /></p>
                <p>Technically,  it's the first and the second room - but the second room is the interior of a shed within the first room, so I don't think I can count that.</p>
<p>There are still some very minor bugs to be worked out, and I need to include some of the new drawings, but it's pretty much done. On to the second, third and fourth rooms - being an allotment path, the second plot, and the inside of either a polytunnel or greenhouse (I haven't decided which yet).</p>
<p>Drawing stuff is insanely time consuming. I already knew this, and it's why I got an E in my art GCSE for attempting to do all most of my coursework in 24 hours while also doing the final exam.</p>
<p>It's frustrating that despite spending a fair chunk of both Friday and Saturday drawing, this is all I've managed:</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper-wrapper"><div class="gallery">
<div class="gallery" data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="3" data-pswp-uid="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11//gallery/path_1_sketchpad_2.png" data-size="720x960"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11//gallery/path_1_sketchpad_2-thumbnail.png" alt="Photo of a sketchpad comtaining, at various angles, a bathtub, a toilet containing a flowerpot with flows, a rickety fence with gate" width="720" height="960"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11//gallery/path_1_sketchpad.png" data-size="720x960"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11//gallery/path_1_sketchpad-thumbnail.png" alt="Photo of a sketchpad comtaining, at various angles, a bench, a plant, a water butt, a plastic bottle" width="720" height="960"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11//gallery/foot.png" data-size="720x960"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/11//gallery/foot-thumbnail.png" alt="Photo of a sketchpad comtaining, at a perpendicular angle, a man's brogue shoe with grips" width="720" height="960"></a></figure>
</div></div>
</div>
<p>I'm giving myself the excuse that we have builders in at the moment, and it's upsetting my dogs terribly.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>I Found the Twine game!</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/interface-of-dotw-interactive-fiction-gamei-found-the-twine-game/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/interface-of-dotw-interactive-fiction-gamei-found-the-twine-game/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/dotw_twine-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-11-29T15:57:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/dotw_twine-2xl.png" alt="Web interface of an old HTML Twine game with multiple choice options" />
                    I previously mentioned that Day of the Worms was originally built as an Interactive Fiction game for Android - don't bother looking for it - I very much doubt it's compatible with any recent Android versions, if, indeed, it's still available. I also ported it&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/dotw_twine-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Web interface of an old HTML Twine game with multiple choice options" /></p>
                <p>I previously mentioned that Day of the Worms was originally built as an Interactive Fiction game for Android - don't bother looking for it - I very much doubt it's compatible with any recent Android versions, if, indeed, it's still available.</p>
<p>I also ported it to Twine so that it would play in the browser. If you fancy giving it a go, it's available <a href="https://davidrutland.uk/day_of_the_worms.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>. It's also somewhere in the menu.</p>
<p>These are the bones on which the point and click adventure is being built. It will have much of the same (possibly all of the same) text, but with hand drawn images, animations, and of course, it's a point and click.</p>
<p>Fun fact: the background image for the TWINE version is actually a photograph of my old plot on the Ilford Avenue allotments that I ran through GIMP.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/dotw_twine-2.png" alt="Interface of DOTW Interactive fiction game" width="1914" height="960" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/responsive/dotw_twine-2-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/responsive/dotw_twine-2-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/responsive/dotw_twine-2-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/responsive/dotw_twine-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/responsive/dotw_twine-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/5/responsive/dotw_twine-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>I recall that some of the mechanics didn't quite work, but can't remember what exactly.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Inside the shed</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/inside-the-shed/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/inside-the-shed/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/dotw_shed_interior-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-11-23T15:55:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/dotw_shed_interior-2xl.png" alt="Black and white drawing of the inside of an allotment shed" />
                    I've made a decent amount of progress this week - although not as much as I'd have liked. The inside of the player's shed is finished - including random plant pots, biscuit tins full of bits and pieces, and a selection of tools. There are&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/dotw_shed_interior-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Black and white drawing of the inside of an allotment shed" /></p>
                <p>I've made a decent amount of progress this week - although not as much as I'd have liked.</p>
<p>The inside of the player's shed is finished - including random plant pots, biscuit tins full of bits and pieces, and a selection of tools.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/dotw_shed_interior-2.png" alt="Black and white drawing of an allotment interior including rocking chair, onions, and an assortment of tools" width="768" height="435" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior-2-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior-2-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior-2-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p>There are a number of things you can do in here, and you won't be able to exit the shed until you've made a couple of decisions that will have an effect on the game later.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/dotw_shed_interior_tool_selection-2.png" alt="Hand drawn choice menu, showing a weed burner, a spade and a rake. The text explains that the player need to choose one. " width="1262" height="713" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_tool_selection-2-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_tool_selection-2-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_tool_selection-2-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_tool_selection-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_tool_selection-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_tool_selection-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/dotw_shed_interior_career_selection.png" alt="Hand drawn choice menu, showing a selection of careers: surgeon, athlete, checkout operator." width="1263" height="718" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_career_selection-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_career_selection-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_career_selection-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_career_selection-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_career_selection-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/4/responsive/dotw_shed_interior_career_selection-2xl.png 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p> </p>
<p>After this, there are a few tasks to get on with around your plot before you meet the worm for the first time.</p>
<p>Drawings continue to pour onto the pages of my B&amp;M sketchpad, and I'll probably scan them in tomorrow, then I have to make some more sprites, and make sure everything works.</p>
<p>I anticipate progressing to the next room later this week. </p>
<p>I've also committed to using the OpenDyslexic font for most text elements in the game. My wife is very dyslexic so this seemed like an obvious and sensible thing to do. It looks pretty good. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Back to the drawing board (in a good way)</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/back-to-the-drawing-board-in-a-good-way/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/back-to-the-drawing-board-in-a-good-way/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/inv_open-2-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-11-16T15:50:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/inv_open-2-2xl.png" alt="Black and white drawing of Day of the Worms playable area with a gardener standing behind a carrot planter" />
                    I'm happy with the first scene so far. The artwork looks decent (for an unspecified value of decent), and things do what they're supposed to do. So far, that isn't much. The gardener needs to get into his shed, but doesn't have his keys. He&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/inv_open-2-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Black and white drawing of Day of the Worms playable area with a gardener standing behind a carrot planter" /></p>
                <p>I'm happy with the first scene so far. The artwork looks decent (for an unspecified value of decent), and things do what they're supposed to do.</p>
<p>So far, that isn't much. The gardener needs to get into his shed, but doesn't have his keys.</p>
<p>He needs to take the ladder, put it against the apple tree, and climb it to get the keys from a bird box. It's not an especially difficult puzzle.</p>
<p>Figuring out how to get him to climb the ladder took the better part of a day on its own. (eventual solution: create a horizontal pixel-wide gap in the walkable area, walk to top edge of lower area, move character across the gap, create the illusion of walking up the ladder using baseline to keep it between the character and the tree, then do it backwards).</p>
<p>Once he has the key, he can enter the shed. The interior currently looks like this:</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/shed_interior_background-md.png" alt="The words &quot;Shed interior&quot; scrawled in black on a white background" width="768" height="432" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/shed_interior_background-md-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/shed_interior_background-md-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/shed_interior_background-md-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/shed_interior_background-md-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/shed_interior_background-md-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/shed_interior_background-md-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>Which is a bit pants.</p>
<p>I'm going to spend the next few days drawing the inside of an allotment shed, along with the typical stuff you'd fiind in there - gas bottles, cups, tools, string, pots, and so on. You'd never seen a hoarder until you've met an allotment gardener. Nothing goes to waste. On the other hand, I don't want the playable area to be too cluttered.</p>
<p>I've also reskinned the GUI, givng the game an appropriate hand-drawn inventory and themeatically appropriate volume and speed sliders:</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/settings_menu-md-2.png" alt="Black and white drawing of Day of the Worms settings menu. The sliders are worms" width="768" height="539" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/settings_menu-md-2-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/settings_menu-md-2-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/settings_menu-md-2-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/settings_menu-md-2-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/settings_menu-md-2-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/settings_menu-md-2-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>The buttons have mouseover images, and each of those buttons leads to sub menus that also have buttons. It took an absolute age to do.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/inv_open-md.png" alt="Black and white drawing of Day of the Worms playable area." width="768" height="536" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/inv_open-md-xs.png 300w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/inv_open-md-sm.png 480w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/inv_open-md-md.png 768w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/inv_open-md-lg.png 1024w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/inv_open-md-xl.png 1360w ,https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/3/responsive/inv_open-md-2xl.png 1600w"></figure>
<p>I am actually really pleased with the inventory and various buttons. Again, they have mouseover images, and the spray bottles are left and right controls to go through the inventory.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>It walks! It talks!</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/it-walks-it-talks/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/it-walks-it-talks/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/2/dotw_still1-2-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-11-13T15:46:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/2/dotw_still1-2-2xl.png" alt="black and white pen drawing of a gardener on an allotment with a blue sky in the background" />
                    Yet another switcharoo, and I've settled on AGS for the game engine. There are several reasons for this: It's pretty easy to get the character to walk behind objects, make areas clickable, and it just seems... straightforward. Sticking this area together from my drawings, and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/2/dotw_still1-2-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="black and white pen drawing of a gardener on an allotment with a blue sky in the background" /></p>
                <p>Yet another switcharoo, and I've settled on AGS for the game engine. There are several reasons for this:</p>
<ol>
<li>The documentation is exhaustive, with many people compiling their own manuals, as well as video tutorials of varying quality.</li>
<li>It comes with some sensible demo modes and prebuilt mockups, allowing me to easily choose an interface type.</li>
<li>There's already an inventory system as well as save/load functionality.</li>
<li>Anything else would probably be overkill.</li>
</ol>
<p>It's pretty easy to get the character to walk behind objects, make areas clickable, and it just seems... straightforward.</p>
<p>Sticking this area together from my drawings, and making it actually <em>work</em> took a couple of hours. OK, you can't interact with anything beyond walking over to it and commenting, yet, but I'm pretty pleased.</p>
<figure class="post__video"><video width="300" height="150" controls="controls" data-mce-fragment="1">
<source src="https://davidrutland.uk/assets/day_of_the_worms_initial_area.mp4" type="video/mp4" /></video></figure>
<p>Animating the main character (The Gardener) took an additional few hours in Gimp.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Good old-fashioned pen and ink</title>
        <author>
            <name>David Rutland</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://davidrutland.uk/good-old-fashioned-pen-and-ink/"/>
        <id>https://davidrutland.uk/good-old-fashioned-pen-and-ink/</id>
        <media:content url="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/shed-2xl.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-11-05T15:43:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/shed-2xl.png" alt="An ink drawing of an allotment shed" />
                    After playing some awesome Wadjeteye games, I wanted to create DOTW with a pixelart style, but after some experimentation, I've determined that this is just something I'm not very good at. Instead, I've gone back to something I know and love - doodling. I'm using&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/shed-2xl.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="An ink drawing of an allotment shed" /></p>
                <p>After playing some awesome Wadjeteye games, I wanted to create DOTW with a pixelart style, but after some experimentation, I've determined that this is just something I'm not very good at.</p>
<p>Instead, I've gone back to something I know and love - doodling. I'm using a 0.4mm black fineliner to create drawings in a style I can do consistently.</p>
<p>I know I can do this because throughout my secondary school days, I would spend entire lessons with a biro or fountain pen, outlining and filling in A4 pages. It's a very particular technique, and I enjoy it.</p>
<p>It would be nice to have some of my notepads and exercise books from back in the day, but they are unfortunately decades in the past.</p>
<p>This means DOTW will probably end up being monochrome or two-tone - I'm quite happy with this, but I'm also thinking about experimenting with watercolour pens. I don't know yet.</p>
<p>These are the drawings I've done so far:</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="2">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/gallery/cherry_tree.png" data-size="1440x1920"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/gallery/cherry_tree-thumbnail.png" alt="Black and white pen and paper drawing of a fruit tree" width="720" height="960"></a>
<figcaption>It's pretty ratty, but still bears fruits</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/gallery/apple_tree.png" data-size="1440x1920"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/gallery/apple_tree-thumbnail.png" alt="Black and white pen and paper drawing of an apple tree" width="720" height="960"></a>
<figcaption>These apples may well be important to the plot</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/gallery/tools.png" data-size="1920x1440"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/gallery/tools-thumbnail.png" alt="Black and white pen and paper drawing of a spade, rake, and weedburner" width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Any tool can be a weapon in the right - or wrong - hands</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/gallery/shed.png" data-size="1920x1440"><img src="https://davidrutland.uk/media/posts/1/gallery/shed-thumbnail.png" alt="Black and white pen and paper drawing of an allotment shed" width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>This is pretty much what my allotment shed used to look like</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
